<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Spartens on Dipl.-Ing. Martin Pfemeter Zeichenbüro &amp; Beratung e.U.</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Spartens on Dipl.-Ing. Martin Pfemeter Zeichenbüro &amp; Beratung e.U.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 21:39:44 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Innovation &amp; Interdisciplinary Projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/innovation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 21:39:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/innovation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to my cross-disciplinary technical knowledge and personal passion for &lt;strong&gt;innovation, research, artificial intelligence, programming, philosophy, architecture, art and culture&lt;/strong&gt;, I am particularly drawn to projects that – at first glance – do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; fit into my classic field of work.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I am fascinated by &lt;strong&gt;interfaces&lt;/strong&gt; – between technology and thinking, practice and theory, human and machine. Topics from physics and natural sciences shape the way I see complex relationships.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Modeling - Pipe Networks</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/3d-leitungsnetzwerke/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 21:39:43 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/3d-leitungsnetzwerke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I model pipeline networks in 3D – from compact plant piping to complex supply infrastructures.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pipelines-are-modelled-according-to-requirements-as&#34;&gt;Pipelines are modelled according to requirements as:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Solid elements** for detailed building services piping&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Network-based** in combination with 3D terrain models (DTM) for buried pipelines&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The transition between both variants often occurs at building interfaces – for example, where the internal piping of a pumping station connects to the buried supply network.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-models-enable&#34;&gt;The models enable:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Clear spatial representation of routes, fittings and connections&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Coordination and clash detection&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reliable quantity take-off&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Early detection of planning errors and interface issues&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My experience in pipeline construction includes both internal piping of pumping stations and transport/supply lines in the drinking water sector – with materials ranging from stainless steel and ductile cast iron (SGZ) to PE. Connecting to existing pipelines with challenging materials, as well as route finding in urban environments, are among my familiar fields of work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Modeling - Solids</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/3d-solid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 21:39:43 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/3d-solid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From concept to form – precise, versatile, combinable.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I create highly detailed 3D solid models for technical, structural and plant-specific applications – exactly to the level of detail your project requires.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;source-materials-include&#34;&gt;Source materials include:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Sketches and descriptions&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Point clouds&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2D drawings&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Your ideas discussed at the table – I help turn thoughts into digital form&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-processing--integration&#34;&gt;Further processing &amp;amp; integration:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Integration into BIM workflows and 3D terrain models&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2D derivations with dimensions and manufacturing-relevant information&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Generation of bills of quantities&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Visualisations for planning, execution and communication&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This results in consistent models that combine technical precision with spatial, topographical and structural information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Modeling - Surfaces</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/3d-surfaces-civil/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 21:39:43 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/3d-surfaces-civil/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Terrain, pipelines, structures – visualised before they exist.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I create and edit &lt;strong&gt;3D surface models&lt;/strong&gt; for infrastructure, water and civil engineering projects. From terrain models and pipe networks to complex river and reservoir systems – these models form the basis for option studies, quantity take-offs, BIM workflows and visualisations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-services-include&#34;&gt;My services include:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;3D surface models (surfaces) for terrain, alignments and structures&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Integration with and into 3D solid models&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Network-based pipeline models&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;2D derivations with dimensions, cross-sections and longitudinal profiles&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Quantity surveying and billing-relevant evaluations&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My background in hydraulic engineering, concrete construction, civil engineering, pipeline construction and municipal infrastructure planning enables precise, practice-oriented implementation – even with large data volumes and heterogeneous planning environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Client Suppoprt &amp; Consulting</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/auftraggeberunterstuetzung/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 21:39:43 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/auftraggeberunterstuetzung/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;clear-decisions-require-clear-foundations&#34;&gt;Clear decisions require clear foundations.&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I support public and private clients throughout &lt;strong&gt;all project phases&lt;/strong&gt; – from concept development, planning, variant studies, authority procedures, RuI schedules, tender documents and awarding, right through to execution and handover into operation. Thanks to my long-standing experience on both sides – as client and as planner – I know the technical, organizational, and economic requirements inside out, as well as the practical workflows on construction sites. Whether standards, project manuals, budget planning, cost tracking, or controlling: I ensure clear structures, efficient communication, and minimal friction losses among all stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Services</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/ingenieurleistungen/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 21:39:43 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/sparten/ingenieurleistungen/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
